<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Election Blog 2024 on Kaitlyn Vu</title>
    <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Election Blog 2024 on Kaitlyn Vu</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Campaign Narrative Reflection</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/12/08/campaign-narrative-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/12/08/campaign-narrative-reflection/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For my campaign reflection, I decided to focus on Nevada. President-elect Donald Trump won Nevada in the 2024 Presidential Election with 51.58% of the state&amp;rsquo;s two-party popular vote to Vice President Kamala Harris&amp;rsquo; 48.42%. Trump&amp;rsquo;s victory in Nevada was declared early on Saturday November 9, beating Harris by approximately 46,000 votes.&#xA;Nevada: A Brief Overview Since 1980, the Silver State&amp;rsquo;s dramatic population growth — including 35% growth between 2000 and 2010 — has increased its number of electoral votes from three to six.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post 2024 Election Reflection</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/11/17/post-2024-election-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/11/17/post-2024-election-reflection/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This week, I reflect on my predictive models for the 2024 presidential elections based on the actual electoral results from November 5, 2024. I assess the accuracy of my predictions with a focus on their shortcomings and also describe some potential improvements that I would implement to my models in hindsight. Please note that the reported electoral outcomes are current as of the date of this reflection&amp;rsquo;s writing (November 13, 2024).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Final Prediction for 2024 Presidential Election</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/11/03/final-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/11/03/final-prediction/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This week, I present my final prediction models for the national two-party popular vote and the Electoral College for the 2024 presidential election. My final prediction models are multivariate ordinary least squares (OLS) regression models using national and state-level data from 1968-2020 to then predict for 2024. I predict that Vice President Kamala Harris will win the 2024 presidential election, earning 51.96% of the national popular vote and carrying the Electoral College with 319 electoral votes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 8: Shocks</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/27/blog-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/27/blog-8/</guid>
      <description>Introduction We&amp;rsquo;re in the home stretch, folks! Welcome to my last blog update for the 2024 presidential election, which less than two weeks away. This week, we discussed &amp;ldquo;shocks,&amp;rdquo; a broad category of external factors and events that aren&amp;rsquo;t the result of campaigns or systematic fundamental forces. Such shocks can range from pandemics to natural disasters and local college football victories, all with potential implications for voter behavior — depending on who you ask.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 7: The Ground Game</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/20/blog-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/20/blog-7/</guid>
      <description>Introduction From canvassing to phone banks, the second main aspect of presidential campaigns is the &amp;ldquo;ground game.&amp;rdquo; The on-the-ground efforts of political organizing require a completely different set of infrastructure than the &amp;ldquo;air war&amp;rdquo; discussed in last week&amp;rsquo;s blog: campaigns must work to identify and selectively target individual voters, while coordinating thousands of volunteers and field offices across the country. Former President Barack Obama&amp;rsquo;s 2008 campaign against the late Senator John McCain is widely considered to have revolutionized the modern conceptualization of the ground game — we know that this side of the campaigning effects voting behavior to a certain extent.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 6: The Air War</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/13/blog-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/13/blog-6/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Turning the page on election &amp;ldquo;fundamentals,&amp;rdquo; our course now turns to examining presidential campaigns and their impact on voter behavior. Campaigns capture the attention of thousands of voters across the country, helping them learn about political candidates and influence the electoral process.&#xA;My blog this week focuses on the &amp;ldquo;air war&amp;rdquo; between campaigns: advertising has both the power to persuade and mobilize voters to the ballot box. First, I create a series of descriptive figures and tables to assess past trends in campaign ad spending on both the national and state levels.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 5: Demographics</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/06/blog-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/10/06/blog-5/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Defined as group level characteristics that can be attached to individuals, campaigns often look to demographics to inform predictions of election outcomes — including the likelihood of candidate support and turnout — and determine which populations to target with their limited resources. As such, demographic conformity is almost an expected norm: individuals are expected to vote in line with their perceived group interests.&#xA;However, are demographics truly predictive of vote choice?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 4: Incumbency &amp; Expert Predictions</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/29/blog-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/29/blog-4/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Whether it&amp;rsquo;s at the party or candidate level, nearly every forecasting model includes some measure of incumbency. Incumbent politicians are often understood to have an &amp;ldquo;advantage&amp;rdquo; over their challengers: they can harness the &amp;ldquo;bully pulpit&amp;rdquo; to command media attention and shape public opinion, get a head start on campaigning, and utilize the powers of their offices (e.g., control spending) to gain constituent favor. However, how does this so-called advantage fare in the face of an increasingly polarized electorate, questions of blame attribution, and incumbency fatigue?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 3: Polling</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/22/blog-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/22/blog-3/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Public opinion polling is essential to understanding democratic discourse: polls measure the will of voters and help to promote election integrity. In this blog, I use both national and state-level polling data to predict election outcomes for the 2024 presidential election.&#xA;Historical Polling Averages (2016-2024) First, I examine overall trends in election-year polling averages. The following visualization contains three plots: the percentage of average poll approval for both the Republican and Democratic candidates are plotted by date for 2016 (March-November), 2020 (March-November), and 2024 (March-September).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 2: The Economy</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/15/blog-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/15/blog-2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the economy, stupid.&amp;rdquo; Coined by political strategist Jim Carville, the phrase became a hallmark of Bill Clinton&amp;rsquo;s successful election bid against incumbent George H.W. Bush in 1992. Larry Bartels and Christopher Achen note in their 2016 book Democracy for Realists that voters engage in &amp;ldquo;economic voting,&amp;rdquo; through which economic distress — especially during an election year — harms election outcomes for the incumbent. However, to what extent do Americans truly vote based on the state of the economy?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog 1: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/08/blog-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaitvu.github.io/election-blog/post/2024/09/08/blog-1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this first blog post, I visualize and analyze historical popular vote data from 1948-2020 to examine the competitiveness of U.S. presidential elections and help inform predictions for the 2024 election. This blog also includes state-level analysis of past two-party popular vote share and looks at changes in battleground states over time.&#xA;Overall Two-Party Vote Share To begin, I will examine how two-party vote share in U.S. presidential elections have changed over time.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
